Guide to the Irma Goldstraw Collection, 1931-2008 (Bulk 1970-1995) MSS.240
Fales Library and Special Collections
Irma Goldstraw Collection
1931-2008
1970-1995
Fales Library and Special Collections
Goldstraw, Irma E., 1923-
MSS.240
8.5 Linear Feet in 1 oversize box, 1 LP box, and 5 other containers.
Irma Goldstraw, author of Derek Walcott: an annotated bibliography of his works, was a librarian at the Alma Jordan Library at the University of the West Indies and a friend of Derek Walcott. Her husband acted in many of Walcott's productions at the Trinidad Theater Workshop. The collection contains photographs, scripts, newspaper clippings, some manuscripts and typescripts, some correspondence, and some audio elements relating to Derek Walcott and his work for the Trinidad Theater Workshop, and to Irma Goldstraw's Walcott bibliography.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains photographs, scripts, newspaper clippings, some manuscripts and typescripts, some correspondence, and some audio elements. Most of the material relates to Derek Walcott and his role as founder of and a playwright for the Trinidad Theater Workshop. Some material relates to Irma Goldstraw's book Derek Walcott: an annotated bibliography of his works. Other materials include publications by and about Derek Walcott; some material regarding the Derek Walcott Collection at the University of the West Indies; a folder of material concerning the Little Carib Theater; and a few folders regarding Laurence "Laurie" Goldstraw, an actor with the Trinidad Theater Workshop and husband of Irma Goldstraw.
Biographical Note
Irma Goldstraw, author of Derek Walcott: an annotated bibliography of his works, was a librarian at the Alma Jordan Library at the University of the West Indies and a friend of Derek Walcott. Her husband, Lawrence "Laurie" Goldstraw, was a Trinidadian actor who acted in many of Walcott's plays produced by the Trinidad Theater Workshop.
Derek Walcott (b. January 23, 1930) is a Saint Lucian poet and playwright. Walcott formed the Trinidad Theater Workshop in 1959. He was awarded the Nobel Prize for Literature in 1992.
Sources:
(2004). "The Irma Goldstraw Collection." http://www.mainlib.uwi.tt/divisions/wi/collsp/summaries/irmagoldstrawcollection.htm
Banham, M. and Hill, Errol. (1994). The Cambridge guide to African and Caribbean theatre. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press. p. 247.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Provenance
Material relating to the Trinidad Theater Workshop was collected by Laurence Goldstraw. Material relating to the Walcott bibliography was compiled by Irma Goldstraw. It is not know who collected the Walcott ephemera that can be found in Series II. It is possible that Ms. Goldstraw collected the material in connection with her bibliography, but it is uncertain. The collection was brought to the Fales Library and Special Collections in 2009 by Angela Carreno, Head of Collections Development at New York University Libraries, who bought the collection from Ms. Goldstraw through the Barbadian book dealer Alan Moss.
Separated Materials
The following book has been removed to Fales Special Collections.
Hamner, Robert D. Derek Walcott. Boston: Twayne Publishers, 1981.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers.
Arrangement
This collection is divided into five series, many of which are further arranged into subseries:
Series I: Trinidad Theater Workshop
Subseries A: Productions Written by Derek Walcott
Subseries B: Productions Written by Others
Subseries C: Laurence Goldstraw Subject Files
Subseries D: General Trinidad Theater Workshop Subject Files
Subseries E: The Little Carib Theater
Series II: Derek Walcott Subject Files
Subseries A: Work by Derek Walcott
Subseries B: Work about Derek Walcott (Press, Reviews)
Series III: Irma Goldstraw's Derek Walcott Bibliography Series IV: University of the West Indies Derek Walcott Collection Series V: Audio
Subseries A: Access Copies
Subseries B: Originals
Subseries C: Paper Material Separated from Audio
Oversize Series:
Series I: Trinidad Theater Workshop Subject Files
Series II: Derek Walcott Subject Files
Series V: Audio
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased by Angela Carreno, Head of Collections Development at New York University Libraries, in 2009.
Authors, Trinidadian.; Correspondence.; Theatrical companies.; Authors, Trinidadian -- 20th century.; Drama.; Little Carib Theatre; Walcott, Derek; Trinidad Theatre Workshop
- Series I: Trinidad Theater Workshop Subject Files, 1958-2007
  Scope and Contents
  Series comprises play programs, play scripts, and clippings related almost exclusively the Trinidad Theater Workshop, very little relating to the Little Carib Theater, and some clippings about Derek Walcott plays performed elsewhere than at the Trinidad Theater Workshop and in Trinidad.
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged into five subseries:
  Subseries A: Productions Written by Derek Walcott
  Subseries B: Productions Written by Others
  Subseries C: Laurence Goldstraw Subject Files
  Subseries D: General Trinidad Theater Workshop Subject Files
  Subseries E: The Little Carib Theater
  - Subseries A: Productions Written by Derek Walcott, 1958-1994
    - Productions Written by Derek Walcott, 1958, 1973-1982, 1998 (Box 1)
    - Productions Written by Derek Walcott, 1973-1994 (Box 2)
  - Subseries B: Productions Written by Others, 1983-1989
    - Productions Written by Others, 1983-1984, 1988-1989 (Box 2)
  - Subseries C: Laurence Goldstraw Subject Files, 1990-2007
    - Lawrence Goldstraw Subject Files, 1990, 2007 (Box 2)
  - Subseries D: General Trinidad Theater Workshop Subject Files, 1965-1993
    - General, 1965, 1973-1976, 1984-1993 (Box 2)
  - Subseries E: The Little Carib Theater
    - The Little Carib Theater, undated (Box 3)
- Series II: Derek Walcott Subject Files, 1945-2008
  Series comprises periodicals containing poems, essays, and reviews by Derek Walcott, some small publications of Walcott's, photocopies of poems by Walcott, and reviews of and essays on Walcott's work as well as general articles on Walcott.
  This series is arranged into two subseries:
  Subseries A: Work by Derek Walcott
  Subseries B: Work about Derek Walcott (Press, Reviews)
  - Subseries A: Work by Derek Walcott, 1945-2008
    - Work by Derek Walcott, 1945, 1957-1969, 1970-1986, 2005, 2008 (Box 3)
  - Subseries B: Work about Derek Walcott (Press, Reviews), 1964-2005
    - Work about Derek Walcott (Press, Reviews), 1964-1979, 1984, 1986, 1992, 2000, 2005 (Box 4)
- Series III: Irma Goldstsraw's Derek Walcott Bibliography, 1931-1986
  Series comprises drafts and notes, annotated photocopies of poems by Walcott, and correspondence--all related to Irma Goldstraw's Derek Walcott: an annotated bibliography of his works, 1984.
  - Irma Goldstsraw's Derek Walcott Bibliography, undated (Box 4)
  - Irma Goldstsraw's Derek Walcott Bibliography, 1931, 1979-1986 (Box 5)
- Series IV: University of the West Indies Derek Walcott Collection, 1978-2000
  Series comprises material relating to the Derek Walcott Collection at the University of the West Indies.
  - University of the West Indies Derek Walcott Collection, 1978-2000 (Box 5)
- Series V: Audio, 1971-1990
  Series comprises two phonograph records, a compact disc, and a cassette tape from the collection.
  This series is arranged into three subseries:
  Subseries A: Access Copies
  Subseries B: Originals
  Subseries C: Paper Material Separated from Audio
  - Subseries B: Originals, 1971-1974
    - The Joker of Seville, undated; ID: 240.0001 (Box 8, Media ID: 240.0001)
      Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
      Format: CD-Rs
    - "Goldstraw", undated; ID: 240.0002 (Box 8, Media ID: 240.0002)
      Format: Audiocassettes
    - The Joker of Seville, 1974; ID: 240.0003 (Box 8, Media ID: 240.0003)
      Format: Phonographs, LPs
    - Poets of the West Indies, 1971; ID: 240.0004 (Box 8, Media ID: 240.0004)
  - Subseries C: Paper Material Separated from Audio, 1990
    - Paper Material Separated from Audio, 1990 (Box 5)
- Oversize Series I: Trinidad Theater Workshop Subject File, 1968-2007
  - Oversize Subseries A: Productions Written by Derek Walcott, 1968-1994
    - Productions Written by Derek Walcott, 1968-1985, 1994 (Box 6)
  - Oversize Subseries B: Productions Written by Others, 1980-1989
    - Productions Written by Others, 1980, 1989 (Box 6)
  - Oversize Subseries C: Laurence Goldstraw Subject Files, 1978-2007
    - Laurence Goldstraw Subject File, 1978, 2007 (Box 6)
  - Oversize Subseries D: General Trinidad Theater Workshop Subject Files, 1973-2007
    - General, 1973-2001 (Box 7)
  - Oversize Subseries E: The Little Carib Theater, 2003
    - The Little Carib Theater, 2003 (Box 7)
- Oversize Series II: Derek Walcott Subject Files, 1964-2007
  - Oversize Subseries A: Work by Derek Walcott, 1964-2007
    - Work by Derek Walcott, 1964, 1971, 1976-1978, 1980, 1986, 1988, 2001, 2003, 2007 (Box 7)
  - Oversize Subseries B: Work about Derek Walcott (Press, Reviews), 1965-1992
    - Work about Derek Walcott (Press, Reviews), 1965, 1974-1992 (Box 7)
- Oversize Series V: Audio, 1975, 1992
  - Oversize Subseries C: Paper Material Separated from Audio, 1975-1992
    - Paper Material Separated from Audio, 1975, 1992 (Box 7)